### Researcher Building & Critically Evaluating Health Surveillance & Response

Systems engineer with 13 years of engineering experience, the last seven of which focused on building innovative digital health solutions. I lead a team of researchers that apply data science and qualitative methods to monitor user-generated content for health insights and build responses that increase trust in engineered systems.

#### Skills

- **Programming:** Python, R, GIS, LaTeX
- Methods: natural language processing | supervised & unsupervised machine learning | time series modeling (ARIMA) | deep learning | survey design | qualitative analysis
- Data: structured (electronic health records, surveys, time series) | unstructured (text, images) | geospatial
- Collaboration: Interdisciplinary collaboration (computer science, engineering, public health, medicine, policy), sponsors (NIH), stakeholders (commercial, regulatory agencies, state/federal agencies)
- General: technical (industry proposals & research grants) & non-technical (news media & public relations) writing | IRB protocol | leadership | engineered systems | subcontractor procurement

### **Experience**

Assistant Professor | University of California San Diego | San Diego, CA Feb 2020 - Current Professor in Dept of Medicine designing & executing a research agenda on digitally-mediated public health surveillance & response

- Procured \$1.2 million in funding from NIH, TRDRP, UCOP as principal investigator within 6 months
- Mentor & assign tasks to 10 postdoc, grads, & undergrads resulting in outstanding mentee evaluations
- Deliver lectures on the ethics of data privacy & machine learning fairness & bias
- Applied NLP to 500k Reddit interactions to discover disparities in topics & empathetic support across demographics in a health community; suggested actionable recommendations to decrease disparities
- Organized ICWSM workshop with leading privacy scholars on data privacy for social media research

Postdoctoral Fellow | University of California San Diego | San Diego, CA

Oct 2018 - Feb 2020

Training in public health (behavioral health & health policy) in Div of Infectious Diseases & Global Public Health

- Applied ARIMA models to construct counterfactuals to estimate divergence between observed &
  forecasted public interest (proxied by Google searches) after social movements & policy changes. Used
  enhanced insights to suggest digitally-mediated resources for people seeking information online.
- Estimated increased Googling long acting reversible contraception after the 2016 US election (10-21 million [15%] searches more than forecasted)
- Identified 97% decrease in Googling for phone helplines following news reports of a celebrity overdose compared to celebrity suicide; findings led to agreement by CNN to include helplines in future reporting.

Visiting Scholar | Johns Hopkins University | Baltimore, MD

Training & continued mentorship at Malone Center for Engineering in Healthcare & Human Language Technology

Center of Excellence for processing large multimodal data & NLP

Combined topic modeling with computer vision to identify themes present in 50k Instagram #HIV images.
 Developed actionable recommendations for public health officials to partner with content creators.

Graduate (PhD + MS) Researcher | University of Virginia | Charlottesville, VA Aug 2012 - Dec 2018
Training in data mining of user-generated health data, analysis of clinical data & geospatial data, & cost analysis

- Procured \$810k in research grants & fellowships resulting in 7 publications with 22 collaborators
- Built a deep learning model to identify active suicidaility from 1+ million text messages from suicide attempters, examined stratified performance for bias, & outlined ethics & challenges of deploying model in clinical settings

- Examined 5.7 million patient visits for 980k patients with 4.5k unique diagnoses from 23 multi-site clinics;
   found that data quality varies based on insurance billing practices
- Linked siloed databases to conduct a cost analysis of nutrient credit trading for the Virginia Department of Transportation; provided actionable evidence for VA to purchase \$2 million of credits

#### Civil Engineer | CH2M Hill | Atlanta, GA

Aug 2006 - April 2010

Staff engineer providing environmental engineering consulting services for corporations & government

- Served key roles (onsite engineer, design engineer, data collection & quality assurance manager) for multi-million dollar, multi-site remediation engineering throughout the entire life cycle (investigation; feasibility studies; design, deployment, & monitoring of large-scale engineered systems; & public relations).
- Managed budget, staffing, & schedule for 44 simultaneous environmental investigation sites in US &
   Caribbean. Authored 44 reports in less than 3 weeks saving \$20,000 of a \$60,000 budget coordinating with personnel in 10+ offices. Authored proposal that was awarded \$1.2 million for follow-up investigation.

#### Education

Postdoc Public Health | University of California San Diego

PhD Systems & Information Engineering | University of Virginia

MS Civil Engineering | University of Virginia

BS Civil Engineering | Georgia Institute of Technology

Dec 2007

#### Selected Publications

Published 30 research studies in top health journals & computer science venues. Research covered by NY Times, CNN, BBC, NPR, NBC, etc and ranked in the top 0.01% of all research outputs (measured by Altmetric).

- Mueller et al. Demographic Representation & Collective Storytelling in the Me Too Twitter Hashtag Activism Movement. ACM CSCW. 2021.
- Ayers et al. Internet Searches for Acute Anxiety During the Early Stages of the COVID-19 Pandemic.
   JAMA Intern Med. 2020.
- Nobles et al. Examining Peer-to-Peer & Patient-Provider Interactions on a Social Media Community Facilitating Ask the Doctor Services. AAAI ICWSM. 2020.
- Nobles et al. Requests for Diagnoses of Sexually Transmitted Diseases on a Social Media Platform.
   JAMA. 2019.
- Nobles et al. Identification of imminent suicide risk among young adults using text messages. ACM CHI.
   2018.

## Selected Awards, Fellowships, & Grants

NIH NIDA K25 grant (\$947k), TRDRP grant (\$200k), UCOP grant (\$25k), UVA StatLab Fellowship (\$6.4k), UVA Presidential Fellowship in Data Science (\$25k), JSF Fellowship (\$120k), Commonwealth Fellowship in Engineering (\$32.5k), UVA All Teaching Award (honorable mention), NSF GRFP (honorable mention), Ch2M Hill Beyond Performance Award (4x), New Faces of Engineering (nomination)

## Relevant Courses & Training

**Courses:** agent based models, big data in health, computational research, data mining, epidemiology, environmental epidemiology, GIS, US health policy, regression methods, machine learning, optimization, research ethics, stochastic modeling, text mining

**Training:** Transdisciplinary Big Data Science (NIH T32), Substance Use, HIV, & Related Infections (NIH T32), Big Data for Computational Medicine (Weill Cornell Medicine), Healthcare Data Analytics (Oregon Health & Science University), Institutions in Context (University of Tampere), Advocacy in Science & Engineering (AAAS)

# Additional Engagements

Reviewer for JAMA, AJPH, AMIA, CSCW, ICWSM, Substance Abuse, JMIR | member, volunteer, speaker @ Women Who Code San Diego, Girls in Tech San Diego, San Diego Machine Learning, PyData San Diego | Spanish student (A3) @ Pura Buena Onda